Guide to the Caleb Baldwin Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Caleb Baldwin papers
1774-1871
MS 53
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
2.5
Schoolmaster, postmaster and town clerk in Newtown, Connecticut. The papers relate to Baldwin's various occupations and consist largely of account books, legal documents and miscellaneous items recording, among others, the cost of education, charges for lots in the Burying Ground and aid to the poor. Of particular interest are two documents concerning slaves and one concerning an illegitimate child.
Baldwin, Caleb, 1772-1844
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased in 1945 from Marjorie Earle and in 1949 from the Americana Shop as part of the Huntington Family Collection.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The Caleb Baldwin Papers, 1774-1871, consist of letters, financial records, legal documents, and miscellaneous papers of Caleb Baldwin (1772-1844), several members of his family, and other residents of Newtown, Connecticut. Most of the papers relate to Baldwin's work as schoolmaster, postmaster, innkeeper, and town clerk in Newtown. His account book as schoolmaster, 1793-1795, names his students and records their attendance, their tuition payments, and his expenses for wood for the schoolroom and room and board. Three folios of accounts, 1800-1820, show the number of letters received at Newtown by place of origin and method of payment for postage. The correspondence related to the postmastership, 1800-1811, shows Baldwin's activities as an agent for several publishers. A volume of accounts spanning from 1800 to 1846 shows his charges and receipts for clerical services, liquor, farm produce, and lots in the Burying Ground Cemetery.
There are also several documents that may be useful to social historians: an agreement, 1792 Apr 16, concerning compensation for the services of a hired slave who had run away; an agreement, 1794 Apr 16, to free a slave after six years' additional service; an agreement, 1793 Mar 28, signed by Charity Rose of Stratford, accepting £30 from Caleb Baldwin to settle her claim for breach of promise and fathering her illegitimate child; indentures, 1793-1834, between the selectmen of Newtown and various individuals for support of the town poor.
The Caleb Baldwin Papers were purchased from Marjorie Earle (1945) and the Americana Shop (1949, as part of the Huntington Family Collection).
Biographical / Historical
Caleb Baldwin, was born in Newton, Connecticut, October 15, 1772. He died in Newton on December 10, 1844. Schoolmaster, postmaster (1800-1811), innkeeper, and town clerk of Newtown, Connecticut; agent for several publishers.
Source: The Baldwin Genealogy from 1500 to 1881 by Charles Candee Baldwin.
Education; Illegitimacy; Postmasters; Slavery; Connecticut; Newtown (Conn.); Account books; Educators; Town clerks; Baldwin, Caleb, 1728-1804; Baldwin, Caleb, 1772-1844; Baldwin, Henry, 1807-
- Inventory
  - Caleb Baldwin (1728-1804)
    - Miscellaneous papers, 1774-1796 (Box 1)
    - Papers re: the settlement of his estate, 1798-1806 (Box 1)
  - Caleb Baldwin (1772-1844)
    - Correspondence, 1800-1844 (Box 1)
    - "School Book", 1793-1795 (Box 1)
    - Postal receipts, 1800-1820 (Box 1)
    - Accounts of mail received at Newtown by place of origin and method of paying postage, 1800-1820
      General note
      See: Inventory Box 3
  - Account book as innkeeper and town clerk, 1800-1846 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1793-1844 (Box 2)
  - Henry Baldwin (1807-): miscellaneous papers, 1845-1860 (Box 2)
  - Newtown, Selectmen: indentures for the support of the poor, 1793-1834 (Box 2)
  - Agreements re: slaves, 1792, 1794 (Box 2)
  - Letters to unidentified persons, 1869-1871, undated (Box 2)
  - Deeds, 1780-1855 (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous papers, 1792-1842, undated (Box 2)
  - Folio Oversize, 1800-1823, undated (Box 3)